<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Olympic | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/olympic/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-20T19:41:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Olympic legacy server setup - part 3 - installing Ubuntu server]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2013/01/03/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-3-installing-ubuntu-server/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T15:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2013/01/03/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-3-installing-ubuntu-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was thinking about a Debian install on my server, but in the end, I thought I'd go with Ubuntu server.</p>

<h2>Ubuntu server install</h2>

<p>I'm not going in to all the details about installing Ubuntu server (debian would be similar), but I thought it would be worth noting the steps I made to get the RAID device partitioned ready for installing xen or KVM.</p>

<h3>RAID configuration</h3>

<p>When booting the server, you are able to access the MegaRAID configuration. As my server came with 2 unregistered drives, it was simple to create a new RAID1 configuration with those two 146Gb drives, creating a virtual 146Gb RAID1 drive.</p>

<p>I ummed and ahhed a bit about whether to use the RAID controller, but it looks like it might be ok kit.</p>

<h3>Install</h3>

<p>I usually use inetbootin to create a USB memory stick with the OS I want to install. In this case, I downloaded the 64bit Ubuntu image and used it to create the bootable USB stick.</p>

<p>Expert install followed.</p>

<h3>Grub2 gotcha 1</h3>

<p>Oh dear, I had a number of failed installs until I asked an expert (@wilbatron) for some help. The grub2 installation in to the MBR kept failing because… The grub2 installation doesn't fit in the MBR does it? I wish it told me that rather than just failing.</p>

<p>Ah well, got it sorted in the end, here is how I set up my partitions.</p>

<h3>Partition set up</h3>

<p>During the install, do manual partitioning. We'll set up 2 physical partitions, one of which will be a Logical Volume Manager (LVM) Physical Volume (PV)</p>

<h4>Physical</h4>

<p>At this point, the menu will show your USB stick (still mounted) and your 146Gb virtual RAID drive. The Hardware RAID is hiding the fact that you've actually got two hard drives there and the installer just sees one.</p>

<ul>
<li>Select the Raid array - in my case, it was labelled <em>146.0Gb LSI MegaRAID 8708EM2</em></li>
<li>Once selected, create a new empty partition (and table) for this device</li>
<li>Choose GPT as the partition table type (not MSDOS!)</li>
<li>Now select FREE SPACE 146.0GB and create new partition</li>
<li>Set new partition size to be just 10Mb, this is where the installer will put the rest of grub2</li>
<li>Set to be at the beginning of the drive</li>
<li>Set type to be used as <em>Reserved BIOS Boot area</em></li>
<li>Create next partition to use as Physical Volume (PV) for LVM</li>
</ul>


<h4>Logical</h4>

<p>Now we configure the LVM</p>

<ul>
<li>Configure LVM (option at the top of the partitioning page)</li>
<li>When prompted, write partition changes to disk</li>
<li>Create volume group, give it a name and select the PV.</li>
<li>Create logical volume, call it ROOT or whatever, mine was 15Gb - this is where the OS will be installed. You could create all the separate partitions if you like of course.</li>
<li>Create swap volume, I chose 6Gb, although the server has 12Gb of server memory, I didn't want to give it swap of that size. We'll see how we go.</li>
<li>Finish up and head back to partition page</li>
<li>Set root partition to be root (ext4), doesn't need to be bootable partition.</li>
<li>Set swap to be swap</li>
<li>Down to the bottom of the page and write changes to disk</li>
<li>Back to main menu and install!</li>
</ul>


<h4>Installing grub in MBR - gotcha 2</h4>

<p>Just another slight gotcha, if your USB stick is mounted as /dev/sda &amp; your RAID array as /dev/sdb you might have to tell it not to install to the MBA, but instead to where you want it installed, i.e. /dev/sdb</p>

<p>Sorted!</p>

<h3>BMC (Baseboard Managment Controller)set up</h3>

<p>To get the BMC up and running properly, I needed to do a few things, first, is to ensure that it is set up correctly in the BIOS.</p>

<p>Enter the BIOS and in the server management section, ensure it is set to use the correct LAN port, either <em>Dedicated</em> if you are using the single port on the back of the server, <em>On Board</em> for one of the 4 built in LAN ports. I used the latter with DHCP. Make a note of the IP address which is given to the BMC and fire it up in your web browser. All being well, you should see the log in page:</p>

<p><img src="/images/smartconsole.jpg" alt="console" /></p>

<h4>Default authentication log in</h4>

<p>Apparently the default is either admin/admin or ADMIN/ADMIN so give that a go first of all to see if you get in. If not, we will have to do some jiggery pokery on the server.</p>

<h3>Resetting BMC credentials from the server</h3>

<p>The tool, ipmitool is required to access the BMC from the server. I just did apt-get install ipmitool to get it up and running. However, before I got it working properly, I had to load some kernel modules</p>

<h4>Kernel modules for ipmitool</h4>

<p>First, I'd see whether it is working straight after install:</p>

<p><code>
ipmitool sensor
</code></p>

<p>if you get</p>

<p><code>
Could not open device at / dev/ipmi0 or / or dev/ipmi/0 / dev/ipmidev/0: No such file or directory
Get Device ID command failed
Unable to open SDR for reading
</code></p>

<p>Then try manually loading the kernel modules with</p>

<p><code>
modprobe ipmi_devintf
modprobe ipmi_msghandler
modprobe ipmi_poweroff
modprobe ipmi_si
modprobe ipmi_watchdog
</code></p>

<p>You can add these to <code>/etc/modules</code> for permanent loading.</p>

<p>Now try again, you should get some results</p>

<p><code>
ipmitool sensor
</code></p>

<h4>Get correct channel</h4>

<p>By running</p>

<p><code>
ipmitool -I open channel info 1
</code></p>

<p>(where the latter 1 is the channel, so if 1 doesn't work, cycle through)</p>

<p>I got</p>

<p><code>
Channel 0x1 info:
  Channel Medium Type   : 802.3 LAN
  Channel Protocol Type : IPMB-1.0
  Session Support       : multi-session
  Active Session Count  : 0
  Protocol Vendor ID    : 7154
</code></p>

<p>which showed that Channel 1 was the one I needed.</p>

<h4>List users</h4>

<p><code>
ipmitool user list 1
</code></p>

<p>should give you a list of users, then you can reset the passwords. I ended up setting all I could to <em>password</em> then, once I was in the web admin, I deleted the users I didn't need and set all the passwords to be more secure ones!</p>

<h4>Set password</h4>

<p>Hmm, not sure I got this right, but I tried</p>

<p><code>
ipmitool -I open lan set 1 password admin password                                                                                                                         
Password set for user 1
</code>
(the 1 here is the channel)</p>

<p>and</p>

<p><code>
ipmitool user set password 2 password
</code></p>

<p>for the various users until I could log in to the console!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Olympic legacy server setup - part 2 - spares]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2013/01/03/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-2-spares/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-03T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2013/01/03/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-2-spares</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been having a bit of a look around to try and find out where you can buy caddies and Seagate drives for the server.</p>

<h2>Hard Drive Caddies</h2>

<p>My server came with two drives in caddies, but with no spares.</p>

<p>According to the <a href="http://www.supermicro.com/products/system/2U/2026/SYS-2026T-URF4_.cfm">SuperMicro</a> spec for the server, the caddy model number is MCP-220-00047-0B "Black gen 3 hot swap 2.5" HDD tray"</p>

<p>There seem to be a few UK suppliers around, although I wonder what has happened to all the drives removed from the servers before sale?</p>

<p>Anyway, here is one which I think I will try, from <a href="http://www.lambda-tek.com/MCP-220-00047-0B-Supermicro-BLACK-HOT-SWAP-2-5-quot-SAS-SATA-HDD-TRAY~cs/B577304&amp;viewOverview=y#productTop">Lambda-tek</a>, price currently £9.20 + VAT.</p>

<h2>Hard Drives</h2>

<p>Then for the Seagate drives, mine has a couple of Seagate Savvio 10K.3 10k rpm, SAS drives, there are a few on ebay, this one seems to be the cheapest for used drives on <a href="http://r.ebay.com/zq4oCB">ebay</a>. Of course, these drives may have gazillion hours of use on them, but hey ho.</p>

<p><img src="/images/seagate.jpeg" alt="seagatedrive" /></p>

<h2>What next</h2>

<p>Well, I've ordered a couple of caddies and drives, will see how they turn out. Plus, I've got an Operating System installed, see next post!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Olympic legacy server setup - part 1b]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/12/27/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-1b/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T18:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/12/27/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-1b</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>More details on the Olympic servers</h2>

<p>Thanks to a lot of investigation by <a href="http://twitter.com/interpipes">@interpipes</a> we now have some more details about these servers.</p>

<p>It looks like Acer/Gateway built the servers on top of one of these SuperMicro <a href="http://www.supermicro.com/products/system/2U/2026/SYS-2026T-URF4_.cfm">Super Servers 2026T-URF4+</a></p>

<p>consisting of one of these <a href="http://www.supermicro.com/products/motherboard/qpi/5500/x8dtu_.cfm">motherboards</a></p>

<p>with one of these <a href="http://www.supermicro.com/products/chassis/2U/213/SC213A-R740W.cfm">chassis</a></p>

<h2>Where was the server used</h2>

<p>Apparently, one of the three letter codes on the server can tell you where the server was located. Mine, seems to have SDC on it, but I haven't been able to find out if that is a location or not.</p>

<p>This <a href="http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:aiCDaaSXo1oJ:www.dalkeithtransport.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/Olympic-Venues-for-UP-Deliveries.xls+&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=uk">spreadsheet</a> is the UPS delivery cheatsheet, no SDC on there.</p>

<p>Mine also has PDC on one of it's stickers, which might be the Primary Data Centre. Try searching for it in your favourite search engine with Locog.</p>

<h2>State of servers on delivery</h2>

<p>The RAID card was loose in the server case when I unpacked mine, which I'm glad I spotted before firing up for the first time. Once re-attached, all seems fine.</p>

<p>I also thought mine was broken, but actually, it was what you might call a user error! What I hadn't realised was that if you only plug in one of the power supplies, then the server lets you know that one of the power supplies might be broken by sounding a continous BEEEEEEEP! So don't make that error, plug both power leads in!</p>

<p>Once again, @interpipes to the rescue! "beeping is just to tell you one of the supplies is "failed" - pull it out (an inch)/plug it in, and it'll stop beeping."</p>

<p>@interpipes also had some interesting configurations too on his servers
"Half of mine had bios passwords set, half didn't, and 3 had a configuration on the BMC controllers."</p>

<h3>Advice on getting in to the BMC via @interpipes</h3>

<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baseboard_management_controller">BMC</a> is the Baseboard Management Controller, an extra microcontroller which servers to manage server kind of things at a lower level.</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>"Getting back into the BMC (which among other things gives you full IP KVM access),</p></p><p><p>first, set up the network configuration for it in the BIOS as if it has been configured it'll have a static IP set the network config is under Server Management, and then the first option in that menu - I forget what it is called - I recommend using the dedicated LAN port setting, which is the solitary lan port above the two usb sockets.</p></p><p><p>Now you can get to it over your lan (pointing a web browser at it being the easiest way) but you'll need to use ipmitool to change the root user password back to something you know (then you can log in and reset the BMC to factory defaults). Using the BMC it's possible to mount an ISO from a windows file share (I think you can also mount one from a local disk when connected to the remote control interface) to install the system from entirely remotely."</p></p><p><p></p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Installing an OS</h2>

<p>Now that I could start mine up without it beeping the place down, I entered the RAID configuration and set up a simple 146Gb RAID1 set up, using the 2x146Gb 10k RPM 2.5" disks it came with.</p>

<p>I also used <a href="http://unetbootin.sourceforge.net">Unetbootin</a> to get a server ISO set up on my old USB memory stick. Of course, it's up to you to choose your favourite Linux distro, Unetbootin will allow you to download a customised ISO too which it will then set up on the USB, so you are not limited to the ones it comes with by default.</p>

<p>The server quite happily booted off the USB stick, so no optical drive is required (my server didn't have one).</p>

<h2>What's next?</h2>

<p>Getting the OS installed and, I think Xen set up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Olympic legacy server setup - part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/12/20/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/12/20/olympic-legacy-server-setup-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the Olympics, a whole lot of techie kit was required to do lots of clever things. As a lot of the kit wasn't required after the games were over, they have been made available for purchase at super cheap prices! Kit was originally for Educational Establishments, but once that batch were sold, I could buy one. So I did!</p>

<h2>Server Model - Gateway GR380 F1</h2>

<p>Well, I hadn't realised that the Gateway brand had been brought back to life, but it has by Acer! The Gateway GR380 F1 - you can have a look at the <a href="http://tinyurl.com/d2xvncz">spec</a> if you like.  It is a 2U (i.e. bigger) version of one of <a href="http://www.pcpro.co.uk/reviews/servers/359875/gateway-gr360-f1">these</a> coming with 2x146Gb drives, lots of memory and a big cardboard box.</p>

<p><img src="/images/big-server.jpeg" alt="bigserver" /></p>

<h2>What are you going to do with it?</h2>

<p>Good question, I'm thinking of setting up a virtualisation kind of thing, so my big server can pretend to be lots of smaller servers, useful for building client sites, experimental things, build servers etc. We'll see</p>

<h2>Where do you start?</h2>

<p>Another good question. It comes with the Smart Manager application, which you can install on it to do lots of clever things, however, at the moment, I've not even fired it up to see if it has the remnants of an Operating System on it. I'm suspecting not!</p>

<h2>I've got one too, where do I start?</h2>

<p>Well, I've managed to find the user manual, you can download it yourself from the <a href="http://global-download.gateway.com/GDFiles/Document/User%20Manual/User%20Manual_Gateway_1.0_A_A.zip?acerid=634213526746016513&amp;Step1=Server&amp;Step2=Server&amp;Step3=GR380%20F1&amp;OS=303&amp;LC=en&amp;BC=Gateway&amp;SC=EMEA_27G">Acer site</a>.</p>

<p>If nothing else I'd like to have a look inside to see what sort of state it's in. Then I need to work out how to attach the funky rack mounts to it, then I need to work out how to install Debian or Ubuntu on it (plus Xen probably for virtualisation).</p>

<p>Oh - it'll need a name too!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
