<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: james | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/james/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-11T17:28:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Before you buy a Berg Little Printer...]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/14/before-you-buy-a-berg-little-printer-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T19:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/14/before-you-buy-a-berg-little-printer-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard today that <a href="http://bergcloud.com/littleprinter/">BERG's Little Printer</a> is now available for pre-order. It does look like a great bit of kit &amp; the ability to produce your own content should produce some interesting rolls of paper!</p>

<p>Anyways, before you splash out with your hard earned £199 + P&amp;P you should, you <em>really</em> should have a look at <a href="http://gofreerange.com/printer">Go free range's Open Source printer</a>.</p>

<p>Not only are they cheaper than the Little Printer, but being Open Source &amp; built using Rails &amp; Arduino, you can get stuck in to the source code, make changes yourself and create some interesting content.</p>

<p>As part of the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance Project</a> we were fortunate to borrow a couple of Go free range's printers and start experimenting. We hooked them up with <a href="http://twilio.com">Twilio</a> and a bit of ruby magic to get them recieving SMS messages. Each printer (Cathy &amp; Heathcliff) had their own phone numbers, when they recieved the message, they printed it out &amp; sent the contents to their twitter feeds.</p>

<p>You can read more on this blog <a href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/04/week-3-cathy-heathcliffs-amazing-adventures/">elsewhere</a> or you can watch our <a href="http://tedxtalks.ted.com/video/TEDxSheffield-2012-Leila-Johnst">TEDx</a> talk on the project as a whole.</p>

<p>So, buy all means pre-order a Little Printer, but have a think about getting the super duper Go Free Ranger printer first!</p>

<p><img src="http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4uf1acC5R1rvn0edo1_500.jpg" title="Cathy Long Cat" alt="Cathy long cat" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
