<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: techie | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/techie/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-08T20:42:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tech companies - accelerate your employees]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/30/tech-companies-accelerate-your-employees/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-30T10:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/30/tech-companies-accelerate-your-employees</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Corporate Social Responsibility</h2>

<p>Corporate Social Responsibility is a huge field in modern times. Businesses vary in their response to the challenge of responsibility, from box ticking a checklist, to doubling up charitable donations, to actively encouraging employees to be involved in Charitable works.</p>

<p>My old company, <a href="http://www.technophobia.com">Technophobia</a> ran a FedEx day, where one of the challenges was for a team to rebuild a website for a charity, which they did. You can <a href="http://www.technophobia.com/blog/read/another-successful-innovation-day-407">read all about</a> it, good for them!</p>

<p>This year though, I've been thinking more about how companies could donate their employees and employee time to make a difference in more unusual ways.</p>

<h2>Technologist in Residence</h2>

<p>Having had the privilege of being a Technologist in Residence at the <a href="http://sitegallery.org">Site Gallery</a> earlier this year, I was able to see first hand what a difference a problem solving techie can make in a relatively small art's organisation. With a Research and Development remit, as well as helping with some of the day-to-day tasks, a techie can enjoy the excitment of trying new things, whilst also being able to fix problems without the usual gubbins of working for a large corporation.</p>

<p>Of course, many arts organisations have a resident techie, but usually they have to spin many plates, from producing exhibitions, to maintaining the website, leaving little room for them to catch up with some of the more strategic things which need doing.</p>

<p>There is limited funding to run <a href="http://www.happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance</a> style residencies, and this is where local businesses could make a difference. By adopting a local arts organisation, getting involved, running events and allowing staff to spend a week once a year, then a day a month for the rest of the time, for example, the benefits would be felt by all.</p>

<h2>Who gains?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The arts organisation - they gain some help in fixing some things, as well as being inspired with new and interesting technology. Building relationships with the local tech community</li>
<li>The techies - they can hopefully have time to do experiments, R&amp;D, as well as doing some of the stuff which needs doing. From tidying networks, configuring firewalls, mending printers, redesigning websites, helping with copy… you get the picture!</li>
<li>The company - they help the local community, building relationships with organisations around and about, increasing their reach and network. Their employees are more inspired and excited about new things.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Who pays in these difficult times</h2>

<p>It would be completely understandable for tech companies to claim that they cannot afford to let their billable employees take time out of their billing cycle to do 'good'. Understandable, but short sighted. It's the same argument about sending employees on courses, or to conferences - "where is the business benefit?".</p>

<p>Well, I believe that good, motivated employees are expensive to recruit and maintain, why risk them getting demotivated, bored and unhappy, when by giving them time to innovate and collaborate, they grow! So the risk is far greater, that you lose good people by not giving them the room to grow. Best to pay out of a sense of innovation and employee investment, than to pay the price for losing them, either by them leaving or by turning them in to faceless, billable resources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Creativity Tap]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/25/the-creativity-tap/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T22:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/25/the-creativity-tap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The Creativity Tap</h2>

<p>Creativity is just like a tap right? You need to do some thing a bit woo and a bit wah, so you switch on the creativity tap and all these incredible ideas just pour out of your brain. There are two dangers though if you use the creativity tap.</p>

<p>One is that if you leave that tap switched off for a while, then all the creativity gets stored up in your brain, without an outlet until... Pop! One day it’s gone, those ideas had to go somewhere, so they leaked out, usually somewhere behind your ear, hopefully picked up by someone else. You have writers block, coders deadlock, songwriters... err, song block. Oh dear</p>

<p>The other danger is that you leave that tap switched on all the time until your brain empties. This too is a bad idea, sure, you’ve made some room in your noddle for new things, but you need a few left in there, to keep the ideas factory ticking over. Oh double dear...</p>

<h2>Writing Songs</h2>

<p>Knowing people who are songwriters, I get the privilege of seeing songs appear, until they end up being recorded and performed, or they mutate into a different song, or they end up on the shelf, maybe for another day. I’m sure not every songwriter works like this, but those I know have to <em>work</em> at honing a song. They rarely appear fully formed but they often appear when there is space in their lives to switch on the creativity tap for a bit to see what happens.</p>

<p>If they don’t have the chance to get the songs <em>out</em>, into the open, then you can see how those song ideas start to play merry hell. The frustration builds, no time for the songs, too busy having to do other stuff. It’s almost a physical pain, the song <em>has</em> to be brought to life. There is a creative imperative which must be fulfilled.</p>

<h2>Writing Code</h2>

<p>Fortunately, for us software engineers, coders, developers, tapping at our keyboards day by day, telling the computer what to do and when to do it, we don’t need the creativity tap. We get stuck? We ask a search engine. We need to do something from scratch? Well, <em>someone</em> will have done something like it, we just need to find it and copy them. We need another pair of eyes? Well, ask a colleague. It’s all there for us, if we use a clever framework or development environment, it’ll probably autocomplete what we’re thinking too. We are coding machines..</p>

<p>Or are we? Having spent many years writing code, I started to realise that when I was mechanistic in what I was doing, I became frustrated that I wasn’t able to come up with new ideas or ways of doing things. I was constrained by getting this piece of work finished in as short a period of time that was possible. No time to switch on the creativity tap, just <em>get it done</em>.</p>

<p>The big problem is when you work for someone else, you can find yourself under a lot of pressure to crank the sausage machine handle rather than think things through. I worked with an engineer once, who would deliberately stop what he was doing and just <em>think</em>. Rather than thrashing through a jungle of code... stop first and think. It worked too, giving a bit of time to turn on the creativity tap to see what happened.</p>

<p>I struggled in my day to day job, so I tried to make time in the evenings and the weekends. But you’re so tired then that switching on the creativity tap just floods you with ideas which you don’t have the energy to either make note of or do anything with. Like the frustrated songwriter I would feel the pain of not learning new skills, not playing with languages and technology. Not actually chuffing making anything which made you say, even if it is just to yourself “I made that and I’m pleased with what I’ve done”.</p>

<p>So, what can be done?</p>

<p>Well one answer, in the workplace, where people have a pressurised, day to day job and a boss, is for the bosses to give people time when they have the headspace to play. With their work, with something new, with wooden blocks, with a great idea they’ve had. Not only do they get chance to switch on the creativity tap, but usually it knocks on in to their ‘day to day’ work too. Wins all around.</p>

<p>If you are your own boss, then plan in time where you put down the work you’re doing for clients or your startup and have a play. You never know what amazing ideas might come to life!</p>

<p>Disclaimer - the creativity tap premise is a load of nonsense, if only it was a tap we could switch on and off!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Before you buy a Berg Little Printer...]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/14/before-you-buy-a-berg-little-printer-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T19:56:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/14/before-you-buy-a-berg-little-printer-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard today that <a href="http://bergcloud.com/littleprinter/">BERG's Little Printer</a> is now available for pre-order. It does look like a great bit of kit &amp; the ability to produce your own content should produce some interesting rolls of paper!</p>

<p>Anyways, before you splash out with your hard earned £199 + P&amp;P you should, you <em>really</em> should have a look at <a href="http://gofreerange.com/printer">Go free range's Open Source printer</a>.</p>

<p>Not only are they cheaper than the Little Printer, but being Open Source &amp; built using Rails &amp; Arduino, you can get stuck in to the source code, make changes yourself and create some interesting content.</p>

<p>As part of the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance Project</a> we were fortunate to borrow a couple of Go free range's printers and start experimenting. We hooked them up with <a href="http://twilio.com">Twilio</a> and a bit of ruby magic to get them recieving SMS messages. Each printer (Cathy &amp; Heathcliff) had their own phone numbers, when they recieved the message, they printed it out &amp; sent the contents to their twitter feeds.</p>

<p>You can read more on this blog <a href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/04/week-3-cathy-heathcliffs-amazing-adventures/">elsewhere</a> or you can watch our <a href="http://tedxtalks.ted.com/video/TEDxSheffield-2012-Leila-Johnst">TEDx</a> talk on the project as a whole.</p>

<p>So, buy all means pre-order a Little Printer, but have a think about getting the super duper Go Free Ranger printer first!</p>

<p><img src="http://25.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4uf1acC5R1rvn0edo1_500.jpg" title="Cathy Long Cat" alt="Cathy long cat" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
