<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Drama | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com//categories/drama/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-25T13:32:43+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fire Drama]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2007/05/01/fire-drama/"/>
    <updated>2007-05-01T12:12:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2007/05/01/fire-drama</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning I was woken by an explosion around 5am - when I looked up, I could see red flickering reflecting on the ceiling, consequently I jumped out of bed, put my specs on and looked out of the window. There was a car, on fire opposite my house!</p>

<p>Immediately I phoned the fire brigade and was slightly off put by a voice reading out my mobile phone number, I suspect for the recording. I said there was a car on fire and gave the name of my street, but forget to tell them the city! Once they sorted that out, they said a fire engine would be on it's way.</p>

<p>I threw on some clothes, got the car keys and went outside, a bit scared in case there was a further explosion. Noticing that Clare's number plate had melted on her car, I quickly hopped in and drove it up the street. The plastic bumper had buckled a bit, but I think it'll be ok. The number plate is just a mess.</p>

<p>Then I got my car and moved it out of the way too, taking no chances. At that point the fire engine turned up and they started to put the fire out.</p>

<p>Don't know whether it was joyriders, just setting it on fire at the end of the road, or a neighbours car which had developed an electrical fault, set itself on fire and rolled down the hill, or some other explanation.</p>

<p>Needless to say, I went back to bed, but couldn't sleep because of the adrenaline! By the time I did feel dozy, it was time to get up for work.. harumph!</p>

<p>The car was there when I left, a wreck, blocking the road at one end.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
