<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Arduino | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/arduino/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-17T17:30:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steam powered Arduino part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/11/11/steam-powered-arduino-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-11T16:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/11/11/steam-powered-arduino-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following on from getting <a href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/30/the-story-of-cathy-and-heathcliff">Cathy &amp; Heathcliff</a>, our internet enabled thermal printers up and running as part of the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance Project</a>, I wanted to see if I could get them running on steam power.</p>

<h2>Steam power</h2>

<p>Of course most electricity we get from the national grid has been generated by a steam turbine in a power station. I though, was thinking more of this kind of steam engine!</p>

<p><img src="/images/mamod-in-the-kitchen.jpg" alt="mamod in the kitchen" /></p>

<p>This is stationary steam engine, hand built in the West Midlands by a company called <a href="http://mamod.co.uk">Mamod</a> founded in 1937.</p>

<h2>Mamod 1335D SP5</h2>

<p>This specific model comes with a dynamo, dual cylinders and a generator, a 1335D. I wanted to see how much power it would output with the standard dynamo. The bulb was a 1.5V bulb, so I wasn't expecting it to power an Arduino out of the box. I realise as well that the output would require stabilising and regulating. Cathy &amp; Heathcliff's Arduino's require 7-16V.</p>

<p><img src="/images/testing-the-voltage.jpg" alt="testing the voltage" /></p>

<p>And I was right! I lit the boiler using three of the solid fuel pellets and waited for pressure to build in the boiler.</p>

<h2>Pressure builds</h2>

<p>Once the pressure did start to build, it soon became obvious that there were a few leaks which meant that some pressure was going to be lost. I kept on attempting to start the engine, but it was a while before it was ready, around 10 pounds per square inch of pressure.</p>

<p>After starting, the generator produced a rather paltry, 0.7V, hardly enough to light the light!</p>

<h2>Best results</h2>

<p>I managed then to stop the engine and hold it, to let the pressure build. Once it reached about 15 psi, I started the engine again and tested the voltage. This time it made it up to 1.5V</p>

<p>After that run, the pressure dropped and the fuel began to run out, so that was that.</p>

<h2>Next Time</h2>

<p>The plan for next time will be to not even start the engine until the pressure reaches 15 psi. I might also try and extra fuel pellet to see if that helps maintain the pressure.</p>

<p>I've ordered some <a href="http://sugru.co.uk">sugru</a> to try and fix the leak too! Will be interesting to see if it works.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Story of Cathy and Heathcliff]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/30/the-story-of-cathy-and-heathcliff/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-30T16:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/30/the-story-of-cathy-and-heathcliff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back, back, back in the day... well, January 1978, Kate Bush released the classic song Wuthering Heights, inspired by the Emily Bronte novel. As well as launching her career, and boosting the sales of flowy white dresses, the song provided inspiration for us when it came to one of our projects.</p>

<h2>Go Free Range</h2>

<p>James Adam of <a href="http://gofreerange.com">GoFreeRange</a> has done a lot of work on transforming simple thermal receipt printers in to intelligent, ethernet enabled printing devices. He’s done an incredible job of writing software and working out the electronics, based on the Arduino device, to get them up and running.</p>

<p><img src="/images/nyancat.png" alt="nyancat" /></p>

<h2>Cathy &amp; Heathcliff</h2>

<p>When our two printers arrived to play their part in the Happenstance project, their default names were a bit of a mouthful, they made a good password, but not a name which slipped off the tongue - 4j8k6i5x5q7a7b5y.</p>

<h2>Up and running</h2>

<p>So, when we finally got the printers up and running, after a few head scratching hours, the first message we sent to 4j8k6i5x5q7a7b5y was, ‘It's me, Cathy, I've come home’ – a line from Cathy to Heathcliff in the song. So Cathy named herself, and 4j8k6i5x5q7a7b5y became Heathcliff.</p>

<p><img src="/images/output.png" alt="output" /></p>

<p>That was in the final week of the Bill Drummond exhibition, “Ragworts” at Site Gallery and we gave the two printers a part to play in the project. Some local Sixth Form students were tasked with sending messages to Cathy &amp; Heathcliff as they jumped on the nearest bus they could find, and journeyed into the wilds of outer Sheffield.</p>

<p>At first we thought they could tweet their progress and the printers would pick up on those tweets and print them, but we decided to mash up a lot of technology to provide a simpler solution for the students. With the clock ticking, we glued together Twilio, Gmail, ifttt (‘If This Then That’) and some custom code we wrote. Cathy &amp; Heathcliff now had their own Sheffield phone numbers, and now you could send them a text message and the contents would be printed and tweeted.</p>

<p>When the students set off on their journeys, they could send SMS text messages to Cathy and Heathcliff’s numbers and the magic of technology would take care of the rest. Their messages would appear on the printers, back at Site Gallery and on their Twitter account. It was fascinating to read the messages sent back to base by the students, many of which were very poetic and evocative.</p>

<p>After all this excitement, our plan was to get Cathy and Heathcliff mobile so they could roam the streets of Sheffield whilst remaining available for printing. With the aid of dongle, a mac and a giffgaff sim card they were freed from the shackles of mains power and wifi, ready to explore!</p>

<p><img src="/images/getonabus.png" alt="get on a bus" /></p>

<h2>What's next</h2>

<p>Although Happenstance has now finished, the printers have been used in Site for other purposes. Cathy has been on reception acting as a comments book (text her and she’ll print your comment) whilst Heathcliff has been reading twitter and printing mentions of Site Gallery!</p>

<p>We still hope to use them for one final experiment where we get them to run off steam power!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
