<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WordPress | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/wordpress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-09T21:10:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Troubleshooting WordPress connectivity issue - could not connect to host]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/05/troubleshooting-wordpress-connectivity-issue/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T14:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/09/05/troubleshooting-wordpress-connectivity-issue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>After migrating a WordPress site, auto update and plugin install wouldn't work. The former errored with <code>could not connect to host</code> which seemed very odd.</p>

<h3>First attempts</h3>

<p>WordPress allows you to download the file manually or autoupdate if configured correctly. Clicking on the manual download link and the file downloaded fine to the local machine. So first, I thought I'd try and download the file from the command line on the new server.</p>

<p><code>
wget http://wordpress.org/wordpress-3.4.1.zip
</code></p>

<p>Zip, it all downloaded fine.</p>

<h3>Extra help</h3>

<p>There is a good trouble shooting/dev plugin for WordPress called <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/core-control/">Core Control</a>. By installing this and enabling the HTTP control, you can test the various transports WordPress uses for downloads. Curl, PHP File open, PHP Fsockopen etc.</p>

<p>Testing all three default transports, starting with cURL came up with the same message, <code>could not connect to host</code></p>

<h3>Head Scratching time</h3>

<p>So WordPress was telling the truth. Now, as WordPress was running as the <code>www-data</code> user, what happens if I tried the wget from the command line for that user?</p>

<p><code>
wget http://wordpress.org/wordpress-3.4.1.zip
Permission denied!
</code></p>

<p>Ah-ha, so it was nothing to do with WordPress, the <code>www-data</code> user couldn't download anything.</p>

<h3>Problem solved!</h3>

<p>Firewalls, I started thinking firewalls and lo and behold, <a href="https://projects.bytemark.co.uk/projects/24/wiki/Firewall">BytemarkUK block outgoing http traffic</a> for the www-data user by default! This makes sense for when sites get compromised, but it also stops some of the core functionality for updates etc working.</p>

<p>Enabling http traffic for the www-data user will make things worse if the site is compromised, but also makes it a lot easier to keep the site up to date, reducing the chances of a WordPress exploit.</p>

<p>The following removes the firewall rule</p>

<p><code>
rm /etc/symbiosis/firewall/outgoing.d/50-www-data
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
