<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sheffield | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com//categories/sheffield/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-07T15:24:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Electrified Spine (and the rest of the news)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/07/16/the-electrified-spine-and-the-rest-of-the-news/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-16T15:39:04+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/07/16/the-electrified-spine-and-the-rest-of-the-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the government has announced a further set of infrastructure investment for the railways. This has to be good news, especially where electrification is concerned. Electric trains are more efficient, cleaner and perform better than their diesel (and steam I suppose!) counterparts. I appreciate that the electricity still has to come from somewhere, but in the main it is the right thing to do.</p>

<h2>Already Announced</h2>

<p>We know that plans to electrify the Great Western Mainline (Paddington to Cardiff, Bristol, Oxford &amp; Newbury), plus the Trans-Pennine route between Manchester &amp; York, Blackpool and Manchester to Liverpool are already underway. These are all good things, but there were some unsatisfactory omissions. The new announcement helps with some of the missing links, but not all of them.</p>

<p>There is a helpful <a href="http://assets.dft.gov.uk/publications/hlos-2012/map-hlos-electrification.pdf">map</a> which shows these routes in glorious technicolour</p>

<h2>New Plans - Midland Mainline</h2>

<p>Hooray, the Midland Mainline, which has been electrified to Bedford for many years is to be electrified to Nottingham and Sheffield (via Derby). For those of us who regularly travel to London from Sheffield we should experience a faster service. Not necessarily more trains though, no extra track is to be laid and unless signalling is replaced, you can't fit that many more trains on the track.</p>

<p>As far as I'm aware, there has been no announcement about rolling stock either, the simple solution for East Midlands Trains (assuming they're still running the franchise) will be to get the existing Meridian trains upgraded with an extra coach containing all of the required electrical equipment, plus pantograph for current collection etc. Easier said than done, but a lot cheaper than brand new trains. So it is likely you'll still be sitting on the same seat.</p>

<h2>Missed Opportunities - Midland Mainline</h2>

<h3>Erewash Valley</h3>

<p>Why or why isn't the Erewash valley route included as part of the plans? This is the line which goes straight on at the junction for Derby and Nottingham, joining up with the Sheffield line between Clay Cross and Chesterfield - it's the most direct route to Sheffield and is useful when engineering works close the route via Derby. Very few London bound trains use this route, most are routed via Derby from Sheffield, but electrifying it would be useful for diversions and could give the opportunity for Sheffield, Leicester, London services which don't call at Derby, potentially shaving more time off the journey.</p>

<h3>Sheffield to Leeds</h3>

<p>Groan, everybody wants a better service between Leeds and Sheffield, the best being the 45 minute Cross Country packed like a sardine train which goes via Wakefield. Why not electrify that route too so that more London trains can be extended easily to Leeds? Plus get some more electrified suburban stoppers on that route. Derby to Leeds semi-fast?</p>

<h3>Sheffield to Doncaster</h3>

<p>Whilst we're at it, how about the link to Doncaster too, providing more opportunities for diversions and commuter services?</p>

<h2>New Plans - Oxford to Corby &amp; Nuneaton</h2>

<p>This wasn't on my radar at all, but makes a lot of sense for new cross country routes as well as faster Birmingham to London trains via Oxford. Incorporating the start of the Oxford to Cambridge route (as far as Bedford) makes sense with that re-opening. The potential for new routes, well re-establishing old routes should give that part of the country a much better service.</p>

<h2>New Plans - Reading to Southampton</h2>

<p>Cross country trains mainly use this route at the moment and it is partially already electrified using the Southern standard 3rd Rail system. Over the next... err.. 50 years (?) the 3rd rail system will be phased out and replaced with the standard 25kv AC overhead system. This is the beginning of that process and also good preparation for Cross Country. Birmingham to Southampton trains will be electric all the way, as might, say Sheffield to Southampton trains, routed via Oxford.</p>

<h2>The Spine</h2>

<p>According to the plan, the Electrified Spine is to be the Southampton to Coventry and Sheffield routes and is a piece of spin. If I had a spine looking like that I'd be worried! The only new route, as far as I can see is the already announced re-opening of the Oxford to Bedford route, everywhere else is straightforward electrification.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I'm very happy to see these extra plans announced, but would like to understand more about why some very obvious links and connections have been omitted. What to others think?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whatever next?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/31/whatever-next/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-31T23:34:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/31/whatever-next</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Then</h3>

<p>This time last year I was in despair, I wasn’t enjoying my job and it was getting me down. Up to that point I’d spent 6 years writing software for Barclays, 5 years writing software for npower/Yorkshire Electricity, 3 years writing software for the digital agency Technophobia. I could feel myself getting stale and much as I enjoyed working with a lot of my colleagues, it felt to me like I needed a bit of a change.</p>

<p>During August 2011, I left <a href="http://www.technophobia.com">Technophobia</a> and set up my own limited company ShedCode without much of an idea what to do next! Fortunately I was able to get off with a cracking start; I was able to share an office above the <a href="http://www.sitegallery.org">Site Gallery</a> in Sheffield City Centre with 3 good friends and then I was able to do some standard contracting work, 4 days a week to get some funds in the coffers.</p>

<p>Having an office was key to me going freelance, I didn’t really want to work from home, too many distractions, but sharing a small office with people I like and can trust was ideal. Being at tenant at Site also meant that I started to meet people in the building, both staff &amp; other tenants. It’s a great place to work &amp; it’s also where I first heard about the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance Project.</a> In a nutshell, the project is a 10 week residency for technologists in Arts Organisations of which Site was to be one of them.</p>

<h2>Happenstance</h2>

<p>After umming and ahhing a bit about applying, I decided to go for it, the weekend before the deadline. The actual application process was really useful for me, helping me to work out some ideas about what I wanted to do next, with my career and ShedCode. To cut a long story short, I managed to get a place as one of the residents and at the point of writing this, we’re 7 weeks into the 10 weeks.</p>

<p>Time really flies when you’re having fun and learning new things and so far that sums the residency up nicely. We’ve built thermal printing sentient characters from Wuthering Heights which are mobile, tweet and respond to SMS text messages. An incredible polargraph drawing machine as well as fixing lots of technical things for the Site organisation itself. You can read more about what we’ve been up to on the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com/blog">happenstance project blog</a> and our <a href="http://happenstancesheffield.tumblr.com/">tumblr </a>site.</p>

<p>I’ve hankered after Research &amp; Development time for years and getting the odd day here or there hasn’t been enough. This residency though has been a mixture of R&amp;D and practical help for the organisation and it has seriously got me thinking. It’s one thing to have an idea, it’s something else though to have the time to actually try and get it to work. There have been nights after working on happenstance when I have not been able to sleep as my brain has been working overtime trying to solve problems... I feel a bit more alive!</p>

<p>The question now though for me, is</p>

<h2>Whatever next?</h2>

<p>I’m pretty good, if I can blow my own trumpet for a minute, at technical problem solving. From laser printers, to wireless networks, to security, to domains, even WordPress. As a problem solver and nosy chuffer, you don’t spend 17 years working without picking up some knowledge of what your colleagues do!</p>

<p>I’ve spent most of my time though writing and designing software. I’m not the best software engineer in the world, in fact there’s a lot of my code out there which other people now have to support for which I apologise most sincerely, but I’m not a bad all rounder.</p>

<p>Once Happenstance finishes, at the end of June, I’d like to take some time to work on some of my own projects. I’ve got two railway related products I’d like to build, plus a project for school kids and then at least one other one which is coming together.</p>

<p>Since being a Technologist in Residence though, it’s given me the hunger to get involved in other things too. It’s been a real privilege working with my fellow resident <a href="http://finalbullet.com">Leila Johnston</a>, she is a great writer, inventor and organiser of exciting events and has an incredible network of interesting people who do really interesting things.</p>

<p>And as I wrote that sentence above, it’s when I thought, hang on, that’s what I’m after. I think I WANT TO BE AN INTERESTING PERSON! So that people can say, "Hey, you know who you should get in to do such and such, you could do a lot worse than hire that friendly freelancer James Jefferies!"</p>

<h3></h3>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week 3 - Cathy & Heathcliff's amazing adventures]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/04/week-3-cathy-heathcliffs-amazing-adventures/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T18:18:34+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/05/04/week-3-cathy-heathcliffs-amazing-adventures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week has given us a real opportunity to do something interesting with Cathy &amp; Heathcliff, we spent two of our three days out of the Site office to get our heads down.</p>

<p>The first challenge was to allow 6th Formers to send messages to Cathy &amp; Heathcliff. At first we thought of hooking them up directly to twitter accounts, but as Leila had a <a href="http://twilio.com">Twilio</a> account, it meant that we could do something clever with SMS Text messages. With a bit of PHP magic on an intermediary server (timescales demanded a quick turnaround!) we managed to get the SMS messages sent to the two printers. Hooray!</p>

<p>The next step was to bypass the button on the Arduino device which you had to push each time a message arrived. We edited the C code and uploaded the new code to the devices so that instead of waiting for the button to be pushed, the green light flashed and it printed without intervention. Hooray x 2!</p>

<p>Finally, we wanted to get the messages sent to Cathy and Heathcliff's twitter accounts - @CathyPrinter @HeathcliffPrinter - initially we looked a using the PHP OAuth libraries to authenticate and send the message to twitter, but as neither of us are particularly adept at PHP, we decided on a different solution. Using <a href="http://ifttt.com">If This Then That</a> and some server side magic, we send an email from the server, via their gmail accounts to If This Then That, which then passes them on to their twitter accounts.. Hooray x 3!</p>

<p>You can see us setting them up on our <a href="http://happenstancesheffield.tumblr.com">tumblr site</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week 1 in Sheffield]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/04/22/week-1-in-sheffield/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-22T16:19:47+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/04/22/week-1-in-sheffield</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're three days in to our residency and time is already flying along. We've spoken to a lot of people, fixed some niggly problems in the office and had some ideas which I'm sure any Technologist in Residence would be proud of!</p>

<p>Our esteemed directors at Site have been storing up interesting people for us to talk to which has been great. It's striking how we've met people who are passionate, not only about what they do, but about the greater tech community in Sheffield, Sheffield itself, Yorkshire and the North! This resonates with me as a Yorkshirebod and as someone who would like to see the economic balance tip in our direction.</p>

<p>Site have a new Technical expert starting at the beginning of May so there is a small backlog of  outstanding techie issues for the organisation. I find it impossible to sit in the office without diving in to help when the printer doesn't work or the wi-fi has gone screwy! Hopefully now we've fixed some of the more pressing issues but it is highlighted for me that I have to be careful with my time. We had decided that we would spend three days a week on-site in the office but actually it makes sense to spend a day elsewhere to allow us to focus on bigger tasks without interruption. We'll try that next week to see how we go.</p>

<p>Our bigger ideas are still fermenting, but two <a href="http://arduino.cc/hu/Guide/Introduction">Arduino</a> kits arrived on Friday and as it is about 25 years since I last played with electronics in anger, I'm excited to see what we end up using them for. I think I had something like this when I was a kid... you should have heard the stylophone I made!</p>

<p><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51jZKCqIj4L._SL500_AA300_.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Something inspiring.. For Sheffield!]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/04/17/something-inspiring-for-sheffield/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-17T17:54:52+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/04/17/something-inspiring-for-sheffield</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sheffield is the city of Seven Hills, George Orwell wrote in 'Road to Wigan Pier'</p>

<blockquote><p>"The town is very hilly (said to be built on seven hills, like Rome) and everywhere streets of mean little houses blackened by smoke run up at sharp angles, paved with cobbles which are purposely set unevenly to give horses etc, a grip"</p></blockquote>

<p>We don't have many horses heading up and down hills any more, nor are our houses mean, but it does feel like we are missing a bit of a trick. The city centre has its ups and downs, steps, ramps and in one particular office block, a slide..</p>

<p>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=twA_mVMgMY8</p>

<p>So if an office building can have that, how about a slide in some other parts of the city. At this point I should fire up a photo editing app with a picture of the site in the city and overlay an amazing 'artist's impression' of a slide. Maybe I'll do that another time. For now though, here is an example of some outdoor thinking in the Netherlands at an entrance to a railway station in Utrecht</p>

<p>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d1uurSegIH4</p>

<p>This is what we want, some super duper slides installed, imagine what an economic edge it would give to Sheffield!</p>

<p>In the mean time, until we do get more slides, here is one way of getting down an escalator in a hurry...</p>

<p>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fFqQOlYE4EE</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
