<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Baby | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com//categories/baby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-21T11:13:20+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baby kit recommendations – part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2010/06/06/baby-kit-recommendations-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-06T20:11:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2010/06/06/baby-kit-recommendations-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In all the rush of our baby arriving, we didn't feel able to start with re-usable nappies, but once we got in to the swing of things, we wanted to try a few different varieties to see what suited us most. Our pick of the bunch are the <a href="http://www.babame.com/flip.php">flip nappies</a>.</p>

<p>They are fab. We have two different liners, the super dry ones and the organic cloth ones. They both do the trick and although the organic ones are a bit bulkier, they both seem pretty absorbent.</p>

<p>Adjustable? Yup, from little nippers up to big nippers... For the record, we started with Tesco's disposables. Although I can't stand Tesco, they got the good reviews and are good value. Wouldn't want to go back now though!</p>

<p><img src="http://www.babame.com/images/flip_reusable_nappies.jpg" alt="flip nappies" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baby kit recommendations – part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2010/06/06/baby-kit-recommendations-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-06T19:58:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2010/06/06/baby-kit-recommendations-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So when little nipper was born, we initially used cotton wool and warm water for all wiping up incidents. No nasty chemicals and worked a treat.. after a couple of weeks though, baby skin can cope with a bit more, so we switched to the pack of disposable wipes we'd been given in our baby welcome pack. They worked fine but just seemed a bit.. well, disposable and wasteful. This is where <a href="http://www.cheekywipes.com">cheeky wipes</a> come in.
<img src="http://www.cheekywipes.com/images/cw/Opened_Kit_Sml.jpg" alt="Cheeky Wipes" /></p>

<p>They are brilliant. They're nice cotton squares complete with dirty and clean tubs and potions. You soak the clean ones in the clean tub with the clean potion, and the dirty go in the dirty tub with the dirty potion. Fantastic, the dirty potion is anti-bacterial and when it's full, you pull the drawstring and chuck them in the washing machine.</p>

<p>Travel bags are also provided and our top tip is to leave the squares out in the sunshine to dry as the sun bleaches them, removing any stains.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
