<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Steam power | James Jefferies and ShedCode Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/categories/steam-power/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-17T17:30:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Jefferies]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steam powered Arduino part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/11/11/steam-powered-arduino-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-11T16:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/11/11/steam-powered-arduino-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following on from getting <a href="http://jamesjefferies.com/2012/08/30/the-story-of-cathy-and-heathcliff">Cathy &amp; Heathcliff</a>, our internet enabled thermal printers up and running as part of the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com">Happenstance Project</a>, I wanted to see if I could get them running on steam power.</p>

<h2>Steam power</h2>

<p>Of course most electricity we get from the national grid has been generated by a steam turbine in a power station. I though, was thinking more of this kind of steam engine!</p>

<p><img src="/images/mamod-in-the-kitchen.jpg" alt="mamod in the kitchen" /></p>

<p>This is stationary steam engine, hand built in the West Midlands by a company called <a href="http://mamod.co.uk">Mamod</a> founded in 1937.</p>

<h2>Mamod 1335D SP5</h2>

<p>This specific model comes with a dynamo, dual cylinders and a generator, a 1335D. I wanted to see how much power it would output with the standard dynamo. The bulb was a 1.5V bulb, so I wasn't expecting it to power an Arduino out of the box. I realise as well that the output would require stabilising and regulating. Cathy &amp; Heathcliff's Arduino's require 7-16V.</p>

<p><img src="/images/testing-the-voltage.jpg" alt="testing the voltage" /></p>

<p>And I was right! I lit the boiler using three of the solid fuel pellets and waited for pressure to build in the boiler.</p>

<h2>Pressure builds</h2>

<p>Once the pressure did start to build, it soon became obvious that there were a few leaks which meant that some pressure was going to be lost. I kept on attempting to start the engine, but it was a while before it was ready, around 10 pounds per square inch of pressure.</p>

<p>After starting, the generator produced a rather paltry, 0.7V, hardly enough to light the light!</p>

<h2>Best results</h2>

<p>I managed then to stop the engine and hold it, to let the pressure build. Once it reached about 15 psi, I started the engine again and tested the voltage. This time it made it up to 1.5V</p>

<p>After that run, the pressure dropped and the fuel began to run out, so that was that.</p>

<h2>Next Time</h2>

<p>The plan for next time will be to not even start the engine until the pressure reaches 15 psi. I might also try and extra fuel pellet to see if that helps maintain the pressure.</p>

<p>I've ordered some <a href="http://sugru.co.uk">sugru</a> to try and fix the leak too! Will be interesting to see if it works.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
